http://www.dfat.gov.au/about-us/corporate/privacy/Pages/privacy

Countries, economies and regions
Select a country, economy or region to find embassies, country briefs, economic fact sheets, trade agreements, aid programs, information on sanctions and more.
International relations
Global security
Australia and sanctions
Australian Safeguards and Non-proliferation Office (ASNO)
Counter-terrorism
Non-proliferation, disarmament and arms control
Peacekeeping and peacebuilding
Regional architecture
Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC)
Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN)
East Asia Summit (EAS)
Australia and the Indian Ocean region
Pacific Islands regional organisation
Global themes
Child protection
Climate change
Corruption
Cyber affairs and critical technology
Environment and sea law
The OECD
United Nations (UN)
Australia on the United Nations Human Rights Council 2018-2020
Australia on the United Nations Security Council 2013-2014
MIKTA
World Trade Organization
2017 Foreign Policy White Paper
Foreign Influence Transparency Scheme
Trade and investment
For Australian exporters and importers
How to get free trade agreement tariff cuts
Brexit
About free trade agreements (FTAs)
Frequently asked questions on FTAs
The benefits of FTAs
How to get free trade agreement tariff cuts
Prove the origin of your goods
Look up FTA tariffs and services market access - DFAT FTA Portal
DFAT's role in FTA negotiations
Case studies: how businesses are benefiting from FTAs
Have your say: public consultations on FTAs
Australia's free trade agreements (FTAs)
FTAs in force
ASEAN-Australia-New Zealand (AANZFTA)
Chile (ACLFTA)
China (ChAFTA)
CPTPP
Hong Kong (A-HKFTA & IA)
Indonesia (IA-CEPA)
Japan (JAEPA)
Korea (KAFTA)
Malaysia (MAFTA)
New Zealand (ANZCERTA)
Peru (PAFTA)
Singapore (SAFTA)
Thailand (TAFTA)
USA (AUSFTA)
FTAs not yet in force
PACER Plus
TPP
FTAs under negotiation
About foreign investment
Australia's foreign investment policy
The benefits of foreign investment
Australia's international investment treaties
Investor-state dispute settlement (ISDS)
Australia’s Engagement in ISDS Reform
Foreign investment statistics
Services and digital trade
International services trade and the WTO
Services Exports Action Plan
Digital trade & the digital economy
International tourism engagement
Trade and investment data, information and publications
Australia's economic and commercial diplomacy
What is economic and commercial diplomacy?
Market insights
Five pillars of the Economic and Commercial Diplomacy Agenda
How the Economic and Commercial Diplomacy Agenda will operate in practice
Economic and commercial diplomacy in action
Development
Australia’s development program
New international development policy
Performance assessment
Budget and statistical information
Australian Aid: Friendship Grants
Who we work with
Bilateral partnerships
Multilateral organisations
Non-government organisations (NGOs)
Private sector partnerships
Whole of government
Value for Money principles
Development topics
Development issues
Investment priorities
Aid risk management
Performance assessment
Aid evaluation
Quality assurance of performance reporting
Humanitarian action
Where and how Australia provides emergency assistance.
Where we deliver our Development Program
2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development
Sustainable Development Goals
Financing the Sustainable Development Goals
Engaging civil society and universities
Engaging business
innovationXchange
innovationXchange is DFAT's development innovation hub.
People-to-people
New Colombo Plan
Scholarship program
Mobility program
Business engagement
Alumni program
Australia Awards
Australia Awards Scholarships
Australia Awards Fellowships
Australia Awards alumni
Australia Global Alumni
Australian Volunteers Program
Australia now
A celebration of Australia delivered in a country or region of strategic significance.
Public diplomacy
Australian Cultural Diplomacy Grants Program
Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Program
UK|Australia Season
Links through sport
Sport for development
Major sporting events
Connecting people through sport
Soft Power Review
Ensuring Australia continues to build soft power and exercise influence effectively.
Foundations, councils and institutes
Australia-ASEAN Council
Australia-China Council
Australia-India Council
Australia-Indonesia Institute
Australia-Japan Foundation
Australia-Korea Foundation
Council for Australian-Arab Relations (CAAR)
Council on Australia Latin America Relations (COALAR)
Pacific Labour Scheme
News
Contact
Multimedia
About Australia
The land and its people
History
Australia's National Symbols
Travel advice
To help Australians avoid difficulties overseas, we maintain travel advisories for more than 170 destinations.
Smartraveller – travel advice
Passports
The Australian Passport Office and its agents are committed to providing a secure, efficient and responsive passport service for Australia.
Australian Passport Office
24-hour consular emergency helpline
Within Australia: 1300 555 135
Outside Australia: +61 2 6261 3305
SMS: +61 421 269 080
Getting help overseas
Visas
Visas for Australians travelling overseas
Disclosure of personal information to overseas recipients
How to access or correct your personal information held by DFAT
How to opt-out from email subscription lists
Complaints
How to contact us
Privacy Impact Assessment Register
About this policy
The Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade (DFAT) must comply with the Australian Privacy Principles (APPs) contained in the Privacy Act 1988 (Cth) (Privacy Act).
This Policy contains information about DFAT's collection, use, disclosure and storage of personal information, including sensitive information, and how individuals may access and correct personal information that we hold.
We take your privacy seriously and make all efforts to protect your personal information from misuse, interference and loss; and from unauthorised access, modification or disclosure. If you wish to make a complaint about the Department's handling of your personal information, please refer to the Complaints section of this Policy.
Who should read this Policy
This Policy is relevant to people whose personal information is collected, stored, used or disclosed by DFAT including:
Australian Passport holders and applicants
Australians living and travelling overseas, including those who have registered via Smartraveller.gov.au
Current and former scholarship, Australia Award and grant applicants and recipients
Current and former tenderers, contractors and sub-contractors to DFAT
Invitees to public diplomacy events held in Australia and overseas whose details may be in contact databases
People who have made enquiries or complaints to DFAT or our portfolio Ministers
Foreign diplomatic and consular staff (for protocol-related purposes)
Current and former DFAT employees
Other individuals whose personal information is provided in, or in connection with, a passport, scholarship, employment or other application
Remaining anonymous or using a pseudonym
You have the option of not identifying yourself, or using a pseudonym, when dealing with the Department, for example, to make an enquiry or complaint. However, in circumstances where we are required or authorised to deal with an identified individual by or under law, or where it is impracticable for us to deal with you anonymously or pseudonymously (such as when you apply for a passport, scholarship or employment) this option will not be available to you.
What kinds of personal information do we hold
Personal information held by the Department includes, but is not limited to, personal contact details such as names and addresses, information about citizenship, dates and places of birth, photographs of people, financial information provided by contractors and consultants, employment history details of staff and contractors and details provided by individuals registering on www.smartraveller.gov.au.
Sensitive information held by the Department includes, but is not limited to: photographs used for biometric matching purposes to confirm identity on passport applications (biometric information); health information provided by individuals, for example when seeking consular assistance or applying for a scholarship; political opinions or membership of political associations, for example when provided by individuals in correspondence; and religious or philosophical beliefs, for example when provided by staff as part of a security assessment process.
In this policy, personal information and sensitive information has the meaning given to these terms in the Privacy Act.
Why we might collect your personal information
The Department's role is to advance the interests of Australia and Australians internationally. Personal information is collected where it is necessary for, or directly related to, the performance of our functions and activities. These include:
providing foreign, trade and development policy advice to government
working with other government agencies to ensure that Australia's pursuit of its global, regional and bilateral interests is coordinated effectively
managing Australia's international presence
developing and implementing foreign, trade and development policy
facilitating safe and secure travel for Australians overseas through timely and responsive travel advice, consular services and a secure passport system
Some examples of why we might collect your personal information include:
to process your passport application
to process your registration on the Smartraveller website
to assist you if you seek or require consular assistance overseas
to process your application for a scholarship or grant
to enter into an agreement/contract with you
to respond to your complaint
to respond to your enquiry or request for information
in order to invite you to an event
to manage the recruitment, personnel and corporate functions of the Department
to hold in a stakeholder or other contact database for consultation purposes
to administer the delivery of goods or services
to process your security clearance.
Information collected for a primary purpose may sometimes be used or disclosed for a related secondary purpose. For example, information collected from contractors during a tender process may be used as part of an evaluation or review of a particular aid project delivered by that contractor. Personal information collected from scholarship recipients may be used to invite those recipients to alumni events. Employee information collected to administer an individual's employment may be used or disclosed during a workplace investigation initiated by that individual.
How we collect personal information
The Department collects personal information only by lawful and fair means. It is our usual practice to collect personal information directly from you or your authorised representative when you deal with us by telephone, letter, email, face-to-face or online. In particular, when you use one of the websites maintained by the Department, including dfat.gov.au, www.passports.gov.au, smartraveller.gov.au, foreignminister.gov.au, trademinister.gov.au and embassy.gov.au and their sub-domains, we may collect the personal information provided to us via online forms on these websites including when you subscribe to a list, register your travel details or purchase a publication. We do not collect your personal information when you only browse our website.
We may collect personal information from another source including a third party where you consent, where it is unreasonable or impractical to collect the information only from you or where we are required or authorised to do so by law. For example, we collect the name and contact detail of guarantors provided by passport applicants on their passport application forms as it is unreasonable or impractical to collect this information directly from a guarantor. We may collect personal information from third parties or publicly available sources in the course of assessing competitive tender and grant applications.
The Department may collect 'sensitive information' about you where you have consented, where the collection is required or authorised by law or where the Department is otherwise permitted under the Privacy Act including where we reasonably believe that the collection is necessary for our diplomatic or consular functions or activities.
How we store and protect personal information
We take steps to protect the personal information we hold against misuse, interference and loss; and from unauthorised access, modification or disclosure. These steps include password protection for electronic files, securing paper files in locked cabinets and physical access restrictions.
Personal information held by the Department in Commonwealth records is managed securely through our recordkeeping system. Staff members across the Department have access to personal information on a need to know basis only. When no longer required to be retained as part of a Commonwealth record, personal information is destroyed in accordance with the Archives Act 1983.
How we use and disclose personal information
Your personal information will only be used and disclosed for the purpose for which it was collected, or otherwise in accordance with the Privacy Act. For example, we use and disclose personal information collected to provide those who seek it with Consular assistance, to assess an application, respond to enquiries or to make referrals. Sometimes, we will pass your personal information to other government agencies or organisations, including overseas governments or organisations, for the purpose of assisting with your enquiry or application. We only use and disclose personal information (for example, to another Australian government agency) for the purpose for which it was collected (the primary purpose) unless one or more of the following applies:
you have consented to use or disclosure for a secondary purpose
you would reasonably expect the information to be used or disclosed for a secondary purpose which is related to the primary purpose, or in the case of sensitive information where the secondary purpose is directly related to the primary purpose
it is required or authorised by or under law
we reasonably believe that use or disclosure is necessary for our diplomatic or consular functions or activities
it is reasonably necessary for enforcement activities conducted by or on behalf of an enforcement body
The following are some examples of how we may use and disclose personal information:
in a crisis overseas, we may use personal information provided by family members to locate, identify and assist Australians in distress. We may disclose personal information to other agencies and bodies directly involved in the crisis response.
if you make an enquiry for information or write to the Department or one of our portfolio Ministers making representations on a particular issue, we may disclose your personal information to another government department or Minister so that your enquiry or correspondence is addressed by the appropriate entity within parliament or government.
if you apply for a scholarship, the personal information provided in your application will be used to assess your application and administer the programme if you are successful. We may disclose your personal information to Australian educational institutions.
if you apply and are successful in receiving a grant, we are required by law to pass on your personal information to the Australian Taxation Office.
if you apply for an Australian passport we may disclose your personal information in accordance with the law to the immigration department, civil registries and licensing authorities to verify information and assist to establish your identity and eligibility for a passport.
Disclosure of personal information to overseas recipients
The Department's core functions include the provision of consular assistance to Australian citizens and the administration of the Australian aid program. In order to fulfil these functions, it is likely that some personal information will be disclosed to overseas recipients. For example, we may disclose your name and travel details to a foreign emergency service so that they may locate or assist you in the event of a crisis or emergency in that country. We operate a network of offices via our overseas posts in order to deliver our services globally.
We do not disclose your personal information to any overseas recipient unless one of the following applies:
the recipient is subject to a law or binding scheme substantially similar to the APPs, and the individual can access mechanisms for protecting their privacy
you have consented to the disclosure after being expressly informed that we will not be taking reasonable steps to ensure that the overseas recipient does not breach the APPs
it is required or authorised by law
we reasonably believe it is necessary for our diplomatic or consular functions and activities, or it is otherwise in accordance with the Privacy Act
it is required or authorised by an international agreement relating to information sharing to which Australia is a party
it is reasonably necessary for an enforcement related activity conducted by, or on behalf of, an enforcement body and the recipient performs similar functions.
How to access or correct your personal information held by DFAT
If you wish to access personal information we hold about you, or to correct that personal information, please email or write to us at the contact details listed below outlining your request. The Department will allow access or make the changes unless we are required or authorised under the Privacy Act, the Freedom of Information Act 1982 or other relevant law to refuse access or correction.
How to opt-out from email subscription lists
If you receive emails via a subscription to one of our mailing lists you are able to manage your subscription or opt-out (unsubscribe) from further emails using the links provided in the message. If you are unable to find opt-out instructions or you continue receiving messages after opting out, please send an email to subscription.management@dfat.gov.au for assistance.
Complaints
We take your privacy seriously and make all efforts to protect your personal information from misuse, interference, and loss; and from unauthorised access, modification or disclosure. If you are concerned about the Department's handling of your personal information, contact the Department's central privacy area, and send your complaint in writing to either the mail or email address listed below
If you make a complaint we will gather as much relevant background information as possible in the circumstances. In order to assist the Department in its consideration of your complaint please provide as much information as possible in describing how you think your privacy has been interfered with, including:
What happened
When it happened (including dates)
What personal information of yours was affected
Who did it (include individual names if known)
How and when you found out about it
Your contact details
Any other relevant information, including what, if any, outcome you might be expecting from the complaint process.
If the alleged privacy breach involves personal information which does not belong to you we will ask you for evidence that you have authority to act on behalf of the person whose information is in issue before proceeding any further. Your complaint will be considered by a departmental officer who has not been involved in the conduct about which you are complaining.
We will provide a written response to your complaint. If a breach of the APPs has been identified as a result of your complaint, we will advise you of the findings and proposed follow up action which may include, for example, an apology, targeted staff training, revised security or storage arrangements, or amendment of forms to prevent similar situations arising.
If you are not satisfied with our response, you may wish to submit a complaint to the Office of the Information Commissioner in Sydney:
Telephone: 1300 363 992
Email: enquiries@oaic.gov.au
Mail:
Director of Privacy Case Management
Office of the Australian Information Commissioner
GPO Box 5218
SYDNEY NSW
You may also complain directly to the Office of the Australian Information Commissioner (OAIC) rather than to the Department. If you make a complaint directly to the OAIC the OAIC may recommend that you try to resolve the complaint directly with the Department in the first instance.
How to contact us
Telephone: 61 2 6261 1111
Email: privacy@dfat.gov.au
Mail:
Director, Freedom of Information and Privacy Law Section
Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade
RG Casey Building
John McEwen Crescent
BARTON ACT 0221
From time to time, we will review and revise this Privacy Policy. We reserve the right to amend this policy at any time and any amendments will be notified by posting an updated version on our website.
Privacy Impact Assessment Register
Privacy Impact Assessment (PIA) Register
Site map +
Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade
R.G. Casey Building
John McEwen Crescent
Barton ACT 0221 Australia
Phone: +61 2 6261 1111
About free trade agreements (FTAs)
Direct Aid Program (DAP)
